[Music]
do
hello everybody i hope you are doing
well this fine winter evening or summer
day wherever you are depending on where
you are
and i hope you're all healthy and well
so welcome to the 76th live episode of
ask a budget today i'm gonna take
questions from
the live chat so
let's get going ask me your best
question but before that let me say good
evening or good day everyone
i can see uh umang sharma rishitrai
sumit kumar ash ketchum nomesh kumar
stay fit stray strong the lonely seeker
seeker
divyajeet
and everybody else good evening good day
to all of you great to be back with you
all again
so let's see what questions you all have
asked thus far let's see what what is
there
um lots of comments already that's great
let me and i will take a few questions
from the comments that you have
placed in the videos as well just to
keep things
flowing
so there were many questions i could not
take yesterday i may take a few of those
as well today
right okay let's go let's begin with
this question by devan
since bharat bharat since bharat is
considered to be the son of shakuntala
who is a character in by kalidas
and bharath is considered to be the
ancestor of the pandavas doesn't it
conclude that mahabharata is a myth
this guy what's his name william
shakespeare
he wrote
a play called julius caesar
does that make julius caesar a myth
what logic is this sir
think logically
if an ancient indian
writer playwright
takes a historical figure and and writes
a play about him does that does it make
the person a myth a mythical figure
if if
today tomorrow somebody would write
a play
let's say
about uh
let me take someone randomly ravindra
ravindra tagore will it make ravindra
tagore a mythical figure
will it make the 20th century a myth
please think logically is that it
doesn't work like this
all right let us um
again the same question
[Laughter]
let's take some other questions let me
remove this one all right and um
akhil acharya says why doesn't india
reunite with bangladesh
will it create a problem if both the
countries unite
um
there are cultural issues religious
issues right bangladesh is a different
culture a different
they have a different religious
mainstream over there
and
it all came out of the two nation theory
and they i'm sure they believe in the
two nation theory they are the
the the nation of bangladesh is an
outcome of that essentially
india had the chance to reunite the two
uh regions in 1971 bangladesh was out of
india for just 23 years by that time
and it's always been part of india so
india could have done it at that time
for some reason which
what is the reason it eludes me we did
not do it today we have
millions maybe tens of millions of
bangladesh's
illegal
immigrants all across india
in every city and town and village of
the country they are being tolerated and
settled by the politicians for vote bank
politics purposes
so we already have them in the country
it's changing the demography and it's
causing all kinds of problems it's
placing an additional burden on the
economy and so on so forth
so um eventually i think we will have to
just reabsorb bangladesh if this
continues because it looks like the
borders with bangladesh seem to be
completely porous completely open they
just
seem to be allowed in whenever they wish
it it almost looks like that
so if that is the case just
reabsorb the country
yeah if you just want to keep on
allowing these infiltrators to come into
india i mean in the last 10 years how
many deportations have happened despite
all the political promises are
negligible
i i don't think there were even a
thousand deportations
in the last
10 years plus
i may be mistaken off by a few few by
some numbers but you know
you get the big picture that i'm trying
to give you right don't forget the focus
on the details focus on the big picture
so clearly we are absorbing more and
more bangladeshis
but we are not
deporting anyone they are all getting
genuine indian documentation
you have a pan card of our card that
city or as it isn't then right so that's
what's happening so i think eventually
india will have to re-absorb bangladesh
in one way or the other
whether they like it or not
okay
um
recently nina gupta won the rama jinojin
prize
and an indian mathematician nikhil
srivastav solved 62-year problem 62 year
old problem
do you think that india can again become
the land of mathematicians just like in
the past yes of course it can
of course india can become the number
one mathematical superpower in the world
there's no question about it
revamp the education system stop
destroying talent
and promote talent see what happens
overnight
okay uh this is an interesting question
can you please speak about the ammonites
and in which era they were alive and
what did they eat for survival and how
is it related to shaligram stone
which is auspicious to lord vishnu okay
let me explain what an ammonite is
let me share my screen
uh
this here okay this is what an ammonite
looks like so it's clearly
a kind of marine mollusk a cephalopod
you can see that they
they're found as fossils some of them
are enormous as you can see look at that
check it out
and you find small ones as well
smaller ones that can be held in your
hand that way but yes people focus on
the gigantic ones
but you can find lots of these in in the
fossil record
and these are animals that lived in the
past i think they lived this is what
this is a reconstruction of what it
would have looked like
these animals lived in shells they are
closely related to the
octopuses and uh squids
and nautilus nautiloids etc
that are uh present today
so this is what an ammonite looked like
they came in different sizes and shapes
and they are also found as fossils
iridescent fossils
you can see it it kind of shines and
glows and it has an iridescent sheen
within it
as you can see so that is what an
ammonite is now let me uh remove that
okay
so
in which era were there alive so let's
begin with when they died out so these
are extinct animals it's a family of
animals that went extinct entirely
and it went extinct ammonites went
extinct during the cretaceous paleogene
extinction event
of 65 66 million years before today
the extinction event that killed off the
majority of the dinosaurs but not all
so these were marine animals that lived
in the oceans
and they died out during the same event
that killed off most of the dinosaurs
and i think they first emerged on the
fossil fossil record about 500 or 400
million years before today
maybe 450 or so look it up look it up
okay so that's the rough approximate
figure i can give you
and
we don't quite know what they ate for
survival i think they would have eaten
plankton or microscopic
marine organisms mostly plankton i would
imagine
so plankton is microscopic or very small
not exactly microscopic but very small
marine animals
there are two kinds of plankton there is
phytoplankton which is
uh which is actually marine plants the
same size as those marine animals so
there is phytoplankton and there's the
regular plankton
so even today the plankton is available
it's it's present all across the oceans
the whales especially the baleen whales
eat plankton that's what they eat that's
a primary source of nutrition
so it's most likely that these ammonite
ammonites would have eaten ancient
plankton from the oceans which was
available in plentitude in the
ancient
oceans how is it related to the
shaligram stone i think such
fossils are even available in
are even found in river beds etc in
various parts of india maybe in
northern india as well maybe i i think
there's a river in nepal as well which
is famous for these fossils
and
culturally uh they are believed to be uh
i don't know
not quite sure what's the cultural
connection they seem to be regarded as
auspicious a form of divinity a form of
lord vishnu or auspicious lord vishnu
lord shiva i'm not quite sure about that
i can give you the answer from a
biological perspective and a fossil
record perspective but yes i am aware of
the fact that these are
held as auspicious and sacred in some
way
not an expert in that so maybe you can
look that up separately
okay let us take some other questions
um
let us see
kazakhstan belarus i will speak about
that separately
uh piercing says
when there are excavations of ancient uh
human remains
why do we
why do we only find male and female
skeletons but not other 72 genders
i think ancient humans were
we need to cancel our ancestors all of
them
we need to cancel them all because they
only had two genders how
how rude
how whatever phobic i don't even know
what phobic it is but yeah they only had
two genders
ridiculous ridiculous how dare they how
dare they only have two genders there
should be a entire gender spectrum right
what do they call those gender spectrums
um
not sure what they call them but they
there is a gender is supposed to be a
social construct these days
in the minds of certain people
it's not biological anywhere it's not a
biological reality
so the question the question pierce has
asked is a brilliant question why do
they
ancient human remains only occur in two
genders
incredible
our ancient ancestors were
well
they should be cancelled for this sort
of behavior
have a humans descended from mars on
earth well show me the evidence i am
perfectly willing to to
consider
hard evidence seriously show me the
evidence that humans have descended from
mars there is no such evidence therefore
i would say that it is a highly
improbable implausible
hypothesis there is not even
there's not even a shadow of evidence
that any such thing may have happened
right it's all speculation at best so no
from the evidence we have there is no
such no such uh
there's no such evidence
uh
if the british hadn't come would kerala
and tamil nadu be different countries i
would say i would argue the opposite
there is so much uh
there is this
fractiousness in the indian nation today
the indian nation is a lose
confederation of diff of wildly opposing
interests
and uh there is too much
democracy like the chinese would say
there's too much federalism
our politicians like to pretend or at
least say in public that india's great
strength is the federal structure of
india it is the
biggest achilles heel of india
and it is the consequence of the british
occupation of india and the
foreign constitution that was
accepted by
by their stooges
when india was
given the dominion status and then the
transfer transfer of power happened to
the congress party they adopted a
constitution and a structure
a system of governance that
keeps india incredibly weak
kerala tamil nadu are beautiful
beautiful examples of indian culture
they would not have been different
countries
we are a very diverse people but we are
one people this is something i have to
keep saying on every single episode
ah
so no i completely disagree
if india was uh
had reverted to its civilizational
historical civilizational form of
governance
then and then india would have been much
more unified much stronger much more
cohesive
and we would have actually been we would
possibly
have been able to create a larger
confederation beyond the political
boundaries of india
something like an eu kind of system with
countries that have
for the past two thousand years been
closely closely associated with our
civilization
the entirety of southeast asia
essentially even china
even japan the whole of eastern asia
was essentially
greater india it was deeply deeply
influenced by indian culture indian
civilizational indian values
and so on so forth that i mean nobody
can deny this no historian can deny this
even if they try they simply can't
there's too much evidence
so
it is because of the foreign
constitution the foreign system of
governance the foreign institutions that
we have preserved after the transfer of
power as if nothing has ever changed
it's because of that that all these
ideas are present in people's minds
because every state has been ruled by
politicians who want to create more
divisions in order to get votes you
create divisions you create
a sense of
a sense of victimhood
then you get votes
right
so so that's
the kind of politics we have adopted and
we are witnessing the consequences of
that it's it's a tragic thing
we need
we need strong enough leaders who can
reverse this it's not it's not going to
happen overnight we may already have
strong enough leaders but the situation
is such that it will take at least a
couple of decades minimum
to turn things around
because there's too much foreign
interference in india which most people
are simply blind to
everything
in every sphere of indian life there is
foreign interference you just don't
realize it
in every institution in india there is
foreign interference it's as if
certain external powers
are telling india how to
live how to manage its its internal
affairs that's what's happening
and these are extraordinarily powerful
foreign powers
right so it's going to take time for
india to rise to a certain level where
we can start pushing back
okay
what's this question arya word is
semitic in origin meaning high mountain
place in north with not vedic is it true
no unfortunately uh this claim is this
is this is the first time i'm seeing
this claim being made
arya is a sanskrit word
and we know what it means it doesn't
mean any other thing in me if if there
is some word in some semitic or other
language family which is similar to that
i don't care about it
it is it is not relevant to the indo
indo-iranian world
arya is a sanskrit word and it means
noble that's it
okay
let's see
some other questions
new documentaries where are they they
are coming we do one thing at a time so
right now i'm beginning to focus on the
podcast on the conversations with
various people i already have some
people lined up
they they they will be released first so
once i am settled in a routine when it
comes to the conversations i'm gonna
start the documentaries
and it is coming
soon it is coming soon by the end of the
month you will have the first
documentary for sure
so let's take it
uh with that timeline in mind
all right um
uh saket says what explanation does
science give for the mandela effect
which many people experience what
exactly is the mandela effect it's when
people have certain memories of things
that never happened is that what it is
a collective memory of events that never
happened i think that's what the mandala
effect is i think it's uh nothing to do
with science it's about a
it's something to do with psychology is
it
not quite sure maybe i will look it up
and
i'm not sure it's deeply rooted in
science
most likely it may be
um if you if you consider psychology to
be hard science
so maybe but i am not quite sure about
this yes i've heard about this that
people have
this collective
false memory of things that never really
happened and
yeah it's an interesting phenomenon but
i'm not quite sure what is the
causative factor or factors
of this phenomenon
all right
guru krishna says i'm currently doing my
msc in applied physics with material
science specialization
can i do an m tech in aerospace
engineering on or phd in different
disciplines of physics well you need to
ask the university that you're
interested in i have no issue with you
doing anything right
but unfortunately the education system
is highly bureaucratic they have all
these
arcane
and
quite often silly rules that if you have
this specialization or if you have this
history then you can't do certain things
every university has different rules i
think most of the rules are managed by
the ugc which is another dinosaur of an
organization
institution it is still mired in the
19th and 20th century colonialism the
ugc so i am not quite sure i i have no
issues see if you're doing msc in
applied physics with whatever
specialization it means you have a good
background in in basic physics in the
fundamentals of physics because if you
are doing a master's degree in any
specialization of physics it it ensure
that you have a good understanding a
good mastery of the basics the
fundamentals and if your fundamentals
are good you can take anything so
engineering is nothing but
applied physics again
right engineering just essentially
especially aerospace engineering it is
all about newtonian physics mostly
so i don't see why there should be any
issue in you doing an m tech after this
or a phd in some other discipline as
long as you have the fundamentals right
so i don't see any reason why not
but well
various universities etc they have
different rules so you will need to
check
with whatever
whatever school university etc you are
interested in so you need to be very
careful in checking that and
i wish you all the best
uh what do you think about the existence
of planet nine there seems to be
reasonable um
circumstantial evidence
that there is a massive object that is
shepherding the outer solar system
object in a certain way
so what we have is that we've got the
major eight or nine planets whatever you
want to call them eight or nine i i
still see pluto as a planet i don't care
what people say
so they are all more or less in the same
plane but i think
i think neptune is slightly tilted was
it or is it uranus one of these two
pluto also has a reasonably weird
eccentric orbit but if you look at the
objects beyond the orbit of pluto
then you will find that they are all
tilted with respect most of them are
tilted with respect to the plane of the
solar system the plane of the major
planets
and they are all clustered in a certain
way
which
you can deduce using uh
using
newtonian mechanics dynamics neutron
physics that there seems to be another
mass somewhere an unknown unseen mass
and a large massive mass at that which
is kind of
shepherding them in a certain direction
so yeah there does seem to be evidence
of the existence
of an of an unknown massive
object
a planet
most likely
uh out there in the darkness of the
outer solar system
right and maybe it has a period i mean
a period orbital period of maybe 10 000
or so years perhaps
so it is still a work in progress not
everyone is convinced but there seems to
be a building consensus that this object
seemed should exist out there
so i think it is something that uh we
scientists need to take very seriously
and we need to
refine
our calculations and try and look for
this object
and try and construct a tentative orbit
of this object and then look for it
there if it is
if it is possible
maybe we could use the new james webb
space telescope to
if it has planetary science applications
to search for this if there is enough
time given to it or the james webb space
telescope is now fully deployed it is
still moving towards the l2 lagrange
point it's going to reach there
in about i don't know half a month or so
maybe 20 days
and then it's going to be calibrated for
there's gonna be testing calibration for
the next six months or so five six
months and then it's going to be fully
operational certainly by the second half
of the year by the end of the year for
sure maybe
we could use that to look for this if in
the in the infrared spectrum so maybe
that could help
all right
um
okay let's take some other questions
says if you get a time machine for once
in which era of history
would you go well why would you go to
one era of history i would go to all the
eras of history and check check out what
actually was going on
so if you have a time machine you
use it to see all the eras of this tree
if you can only use it for once maybe
the vedic era maybe ten thousand years
before today's to so so as to understand
uh
what our ancestors were like what the
lifestyle and culture was like and what
the great river saraswati was like in
those days so maybe that would be the
era maybe
between five and ten thousand years
before today that's maybe where i would
go if i had only one opportunity to use
the time machine
and otherwise i don't mind looking into
the future as well you know
right interesting
question
i have spoken about ram situ multiple
times
what was the role of world war ii in the
independence of india well multiple
see it's not just a single linear thing
there are multiple effects
of the second world war first of all it
nearly bankrupted the uk it nearly
bankrupted britain
and by this time there was nothing left
in india to plunder india had been
totally destroyed and sucked dry
and
it was too much of an effort for the
british to administer this entire
subcontinent from so far away so they
thought let's cut our losses and get out
of india there's nothing more
to be uh gained from
hanging on to india so that is one thing
that's what
hastened the
transfer of power to the congress party
the second thing is that the indian
soldiers who fought for the british in
the indian army the indian navy the
royal indian navy and so on
they
were becoming
very dissatisfied with the british and
they saw what was happening
uh with respect to nitaj subhash and the
rebels and the indian national army and
they were very
dissatisfied
and this sense of nationalism patriotism
was growing among them
and then there was the the so-called
indian navy revolt royal indian navy
revolt or
rebellion or whatever you want to call
it
and
they were able to um
quell it with the help of the congress
party leaders like mr patel
who gave certain assurances with that
which were never kept which were
immediately broken but by this time the
british knew that india is a virtual
tinderbox it's like a ticking bomb
the indian armed forces are becoming
restless nationalistic and they see us
as foreign occupiers of india
right
so these are the effects of
some of the effects of the second world
war
and the first half of the 20th century
was quite pivotal in
what happened in india for instance you
had the
unnecessary and completely completely
unnecessary involvement in the khilafat
movement in india which was all done by
mr gandhi mr gandhi
what was the need to do that and
all of that so there are multiple causes
multiple factors that all accumulated
in the british
withdrawal from india the hasty
the hasty the harid withdrawal from
india
but things went
well they were able to ensure that their
puppets their stooges were put in place
in india so it was a transfer of power
15th of august 1947 was not independence
fyi my friends it was not india's
independence it was dominion status
india became a republic in 1950 or
something
check out the details
and that too it became a colonized
republic nothing has changed
the same institutions where continued
foreign
a foreign constitution was imposed upon
india without the consent of the indian
people
which is completely undemocratic
when you imp when you write a new
constitution it has to be put to a vote
a referendum that do you the people of
india accept this or do you reject it
this opportunity was never given to the
people of india who the hell were the
was the constituent assembly to say that
they represented the will of the people
of india they represented the will of
less than 13 of the people of india
so these
facts have been hidden from you all
so we are today not independent we are
still under shackles we are still
unfree we are still colonized
and
99 of indians don't even know that they
don't even realize that
sheep
i do not mean to disrespect but this is
the attitude that sheep have they
live in their nice happy world the good
shepherd is taking care of us every day
we don't have to work we can just relax
eat grass all day we have a nice shave
safe shelter to sleep in in the night we
have kids our kids are also taking care
of everything is hunky dory until one
fine day one fine day in the morning
when you end up in the slaughterhouse
but it happens one by one so you don't
realize you think your friend who went
off to some place maybe he's gone to a
better place or she has gone to a better
place
so you never know what's happening so
that's the situation in india today
unfortunately
what to do them
firstly edu get yourself
once you understand what's happening
educate your friends and family
speak about this if you can write write
about this speak about this spread the
word once there is a critical mass of
understanding the current system will no
longer be tenable
it's not going to happen tomorrow or
next week or next month
but if if we all speak about this if we
spread the awareness in the next 20
years you're gonna have different kinds
of leaders coming out of india
especially the young people they will
have a different understanding they will
have a correct picture of india
so it thinks
see that the union unit of change in
history the unit of time
in history and in geopolitics
is the decade if you look at events at
sub decade level levels you will see
almost no change happening you will see
that everything is the same but if you
look at a nation or a period of history
from a decade decade by decade level
then you will see how changes happen
so i would say it will take at least a
couple of decades for the for a
significant
change to happen from the point of view
of awareness among the youth among the
youngsters the old folks they're never
going to change they're not going to
change their mindset their mindset is
set in stone
so all we need to do is ensure that the
youngsters are made aware of this two
days 10 year olds 12 year olds 15 years
old 20 year olds 25 year olds these
young people still i have an open mind
as you get older your mind gets closed
and rigid
youngsters are open to new ideas they
are open to seeing the truth they want
the truth youngsters are rebellious by
nature it's a good thing
right
so it's they who hold the keys to the
future of the civilization and what
needs to be done is this all of this
needs to be communicated not by one
person 10 people by all of you
by all of you so do that
it's a you know there is power in
numbers and we have the numbers you know
so that's what needs to happen
all right
please speak about the ninjas and the
samurai
well
um
maybe i should bring in an expert from
japan to talk about this but the samurai
were the were essentially the katrias of
japan
in the past thousand plus years
uh they were the protectors of the realm
they were also from time to time great
warlords they even became
de facto rulers of japan from time to
time in different eras they also had
internecine warfare
they used to fight each other from time
to time and all but they had what is
known as the code of the samurai the
bushido code
which is a set of moral principles that
they would live and die by
right so they would die for the code and
they had a very clear set of rules and
principles that they
absolutely adhered to
the your honor was was more important
than your life
and the practice of seppuku or harakiri
is part of that you know once you feel
that you have dishonored yourself and
your people in your nation
in your culture or whatever
it is better to
commit
in a ritual manner which essentially uh
restores
the honor that you you lost so that is
what the samurai were they are very very
well their their
their mission their lifestyle their
code of honor
it is essentially in a way
very much the same as the code of honor
of the chatria people of india or the
rajputs of india
honor was paramount duty was paramount
respecting your elders respecting women
respecting and so on so forth you know
so that's what bushido was that was the
code of the samurai
and the samurai were destroyed as an
institution in the late 19th century by
the meiji emperor during the so-called
meiji restoration
so they were traditionalists the samurai
they refused to fight with modern
weapons
do you see parallels with certain indian
peoples
so they were traditionalists they were
they they believed in tradition they
refused to fight with modern weapons
you would have these uh soldiers
standing with rifles and they somehow i
would take out a sword charge and die in
the process
so their refusal to change with the time
led to their demise
and they essentially were
marginalized and destroyed as an
institution in the late 19th century by
the meiji emperor during the meiji
restoration who were the ninjas the
ninjas were the ninjas essentially were
assassins
they were assassins in japan so that's a
very small subset
of the people of japan
and they had this art called ninjutsu
which was the art of the ninja and they
had certain specific weapons
the shuriken which is the the
star-shaped uh throwing
um
a throwing weapon it's shaped like a
star
and they would also use various toxins
poisons and they were really good at
uh being stealthy and so on and so forth
so that's what the ninjas were
i am giving you a very very uh
brief outline it's a fascinating topic
that you have brought out
maybe in the future if i can get in
touch with some expert from japan about
these topics then maybe i can
do that so i'll put that on my to-do
list long-term to-do list
how are we still colonized
figure it out sir i just laid it out in
excruciating detail so please figure it
out
gautam buddha got enlightenment at
buddha gaya but in the present day
nobody follows buddhism here in buddha
bihar why
you know
western civilization emerged out of
ancient greek culture nobody practices
ancient greek culture or religion in
greece why
why
because it was destroyed by the
abrahamic cults
right
similarly what happened to the practice
of buddhist
to what happened to buddhist practices
in
magadh in bihar
it was all eradicated uprooted destroyed
to the last person by the turks by the
invading turks
today's marxist historians try to
portray hinduism
they call it brahmanism as the force
that destroyed
buddhist practices in india that is
completely not true
totally not true
firstly i have said this and i'm going
to keep saying it buddhism and hinduism
are not separate things
there may be minute differences and
indians
simply lack the understanding of the big
picture
view of things indians only want to
concentrate on small tiny minute things
and then load them out of proportion and
it is not your fault my dear friends it
is the education system that does that
they ask you to write
an essay in the exam and you make one
small spelling mistake somewhere you get
one name wrong you say 15 32 instead of
15 31 then you will get half the marks
then half the marks will be detected so
indians are forced to only focus from
childhood on small minor deals with and
they simply never understand how to look
at the big picture
and that's why indians think they have
been led to believe that buddhism and
hinduism are separate because there is
these small little one or two
differences between them
but look at the values they are the same
values look at the principles they're
the same principles
look at the belief in karma it's the
same
99.9 of things are the same
look at the practice of buddhism in
thailand in in vietnam in japan in korea
look at the deities the worshipers
buddhist deities these are all hindu
gods but people simply won't see that
they won't see the big picture they will
look at tiny details please change your
mindset my dear friends please i implore
you so buddhism hinduism are not
separate things
in the great university of nalanda and
other places they taught the vedas as
well but nalanda is portrayed as a
buddhist university for some reason by
india's so-called scholars who are liars
everything was taught in nalanda
the buddhist precepts of the of the lord
buddha the vedic precepts the vedas the
puranas the operations everything was
taught in nalanda when you look at the
so-called buddhist scholars who went to
china and exported indian texts do you
know how many vedic texts were exported
do you know that they were also experts
in the four vedas they will not tell you
this kumarajeeva the great kumara jiva
whose statues you will find all across
in across uh
china and chinese occupied territories
he was an expert in the four vedas apart
from the precept of the buddha they will
not tell you this buddhism hinduism is
the same thing when the turks came to
india invaded and occupied india they
had seen mainly what are called buddhist
practices across central asia because
that was a prevalent flavor of dharma
which was prevalent in central asia
so they called these statues but
and wherever the soap
practices
that looked like the practices they had
seen in central asia they wanted to
destroy them because they were
barbarians
barbarians not by blood but barbarians
by behavior
murderers
genocidal maniacs that's what they were
the same turks
defended india
in the turkish dynasty in gandhar
the same huns became part of indian
culture
but their descendants later on became
the monsters who destroyed much of india
and indian culture so the turks they saw
whenever they saw something that looked
like the buddhism they had seen in
central asia they wanted to approve an
eradicated eradicate that so that's why
they destroyed all of india's universes
because there was
there were aspects of buddhism quite
visible there so they destroyed all of
india's universities they beheaded tens
of thousands hundreds of thousands of
teachers and monks and students millions
and millions
and that's why
wherever they saw buddhism they killed
the teachers the practitioners
the and destroyed libraries universities
and all that that's why
what you guys call hinduism still
survive because they did not go for it
in with that viciousness they went for
what they perceived as the
both the practices
so it is a turk that eradicated what you
guys call buddhism from india not just
from both but across
the indian subcontinent from gandhar to
vanga vanga pradesh bengal
and i would say in the south also even
eventually
they never conquered lanka
which is why
lanka is still
you will see
that the sinhalese people they practice
what is called buddhism today
right and they did not conquer southeast
asia which is why thailand burma
and all the southeast asian countries
they practice
what we call
buddhism but in thailand you will see
the worship of ganesh everywhere the
worship of vishnu everywhere now are
these buddhist gods no they are dharmic
gods for god's sake
right
so that's the answer my dear friends
and i would request you all
i would like to request you all that
when i say these things
i am showing you a certain path a
certain direction i am hoping
that you guys will do some of your own
research and study this further how do
you do it do a google search
and look at the first 50
results in detail
it takes time i'm not going to spoon
feed you with facts and details and
references
it's going gonna take time for you to
understand this properly you think i i
learned this in a or a weekend
so please do your own research i can
show you the direction i cannot spoon
feed you it is not feasible for me to
spoon feed you
i am giving you
the information that i have whatever i
have learned over the decades
please do your own research you are all
intelligent people
all of you please use that intelligence
please dis rediscover it and use it
be curious ask questions go to google or
whatever your favorite search engine is
and examine all of this in great detail
all the information
is available in the public domain you
just need to know how to look for it
so please please do that
all right uh let me take
um
some questions that were asked in the
previous comments so there is one here
wanted to know the roots of
vegetarianism are humans anatomically
omnivore or vegetarians or is it for
survival
this is an interesting question so if
you look at the human digestive system
the length of the intestines etc it is
quite short
compared to herbivorous animals like
cattle cows buffalos deer
right the human digestive system is
shorter
than herbivorous animals that is one
piece of evidence the intestines if you
look at if you lay it out in a straight
line it's going to be much shorter
than that of a herbivorous animal number
two
our teeth
are flat
we don't have those
dracula teeth right i mean we do have
some canines for canine teeth but that's
it
so it's a
vestige from a much older time whenever
our ancestors
may have been purely may may have been
purely
carnivorous animals perhaps like 50
million years before today when our
ancestors were rat like or
shrew like creatures mammals
but today we have flat teeth which
indicates that we may have been
in the recent past primarily
vegetarian primarily
but our digestive system is short
when you are a herbivorous animal a
ruminant animal you have a much much
much more extended digestive system cows
and buffaloes and cattle have multiple
stomachs we only have one which also
indicates that in recent times
we have been consuming meat our
ancestors have been consuming meat maybe
in the last million two million years if
you look at our closest cousins
our closest relatives
the chimpanzees in the gorillas the
chimpanzees are omnivores they eat
whatever whatever comes to their hand
they even engage in cannibalism other
monkeys at times or even sometimes other
chimpanzees
brutal vicious
wild
savage violent apes like us
our other cousins the gorillas are
purely vegetarian
so it's a mixed bag so from the evidence
we have our teeth indicate we are
primarily vegetarian we do have some
canine
teeth i think four cannon teeth maybe
more if you're a dentist you may you may
correct me look at the big picture
please
and our digestive system is shorter than
that of a typical herbivorous animal
which indicates that we are omnivores
we are omnivores now the roots of
vegetarianism in india are
philosophical cultural spiritual
we lived our ancestors in the past 70
000 years lived in the indian
subcontinent in a land of plenty
everything you could ask the gods for
was available
right
we had lush forests
amazing
fruit trees
very fertile soil this beautiful monsoon
twice a year in some places and so on so
you could develop
agriculture you could grow things
and you had so so many plant plentiful
vegetables and fruits
so i think after our ancestors settled
down in india there was no need for
for competition because it is such a
vast land such a plentiful land that
there was plenty for everybody so india
became a peaceful society in the past 70
000 years and a certain kind of culture
developed the dharmic culture
so it's a peaceful culture it's a it's
the highest civilization the world has
ever seen
that we know of right
so the
the idea of
eschewing unnecessary violence was
at the heart of dharmic culture
right
so don't cause unnecessary suffering to
anything whether it's plants animals
whatever you need to eat fruits and
vegetables but why unnecessary
unnecessarily kill animals when you can
get the same nutrition from plants so
it's a cultural
concept it's at the heart of dharma and
it's not
mandated for everybody
historically people who are warriors
would have eaten meat
right
and and we have evidence of of
of meat eating that we find from place
to place time to time
in the ancient historical archaeological
record in india it is undeniable we find
fishing hooks we find uh bones of
various animals with cut marks and burn
marks on the on them which is a telltale
sign of what happened but india for the
past i don't know how many thousand
years has been primarily vegetarian
because of cultural philosophical
spiritual
or so you can call it religious reasons
there was no need for this you could get
your nutrition as much as you wanted
from other sources so don't
hurt other living beings
unnecessarily so that is the roots of
vegetarianism
i think the dharmic culture is the only
culture that i know of that emphasizes
the superiority
of a non-violent life and a vegetarian
life
but it's not forced or imposed
upon anyone
so that's what i can say
about this an interesting question let
us see some more live questions
um
[Music]
are there any mentions of brahmins
eating meat and drinking wine you know
what i am not an expert in this i have
not gone through millions of pages of
ancient literature
so
my answer is i don't know
i don't know
most likely you would not find too many
mentions in ancient literature
of the priestly class of indians
eating meat and drinking wine but you
would certainly find
mentions of the warrior class of people
and the
the classes of people that engaged in
physical hard physical labor they would
have eaten meat and i would not be
surprised to see that but i don't have a
definitive answer because i have not
studied this particular
uh question in detail
all right
what's the origin of galia or abusive
words in our day-to-day language did the
mughals and british introduce them did
ancient indians use them you know
abusive words uh
that are spoken
in the vernacular languages in india are
mostly of persian origin i would say i'm
not going to repeat those words
but not the british
the persians
and the turks introduced the persian
language into india the so-called
mughals were actually turks
and
they used persian as the office language
of india because they had this
inferiority complex they considered
persian to be a superior culture to them
so they used persian as the court
language
while they were occupying india
the so-called mughals
and because of that various persian
words
entered
common palace in india especially in
northern and western india you will see
languages like gujarati are full of
persian words and arabic words as well
gujarati people
wish each other happy new year the
gujarati new year by saying sal mubarak
there you see and you will see lots of
other
other such persian and arabic and even
turkic words
that are quite prevalent in the
languages of northern india as well
there are lots of examples i'm not going
into that so most of these abusive
cross-crewed words came in with these
languages
through introgression and infiltration
and occupation right
but can you claim that ancient indians
did not use abusive language i
will not make that claim
study sanskrit you will find
that every word you can imagine is
present either as a pure word or as a
sandhi
there are certain abusive words in
let's say russian
which are the equivalent of certain
english four-letter words
which have sanskrit roots
so i
so it is incorrect to believe that our
ancient ancestors
during the classical era the classical
sanskrit and the vedic would never have
used abusive language come on we're
human beings we had higher culture at
the time but
people are people right we have the same
emotions the same everything
and
the thing about sanskrit is that there
are so many synonyms for any word you
can imagine
the word for love has more than 90
synonyms in sanskrit
the word for snow snow there's more than
i think 10 or 20 synonyms on sanskrit
different kinds of snow in different
contexts
and so on and so forth
so sanskrit is such a rich language that
you will find synonyms for everything in
there multiple synonyms for various
things
so i would encourage you to kindly look
into it there are online sanskrit
dictionaries that you can find i will
not give you the link
google it
use your curiosity look it up come on
guys and girls
right
was mr gandhi secretly a british mole on
a mission to destroy hindu culture i
will leave that judgment to you
i have spoken about various facts
recorded facts about mr gandhi
on many occasions
i have given references
to books about mr gandhi
modern books about mr gandhi with
factual data in them on multiple
locations please look through that and i
will
leave this judgment the final judgment
to all of you
please use the data i have provided
and please use your own intelligence and
wisdom to come to a conclusion
so here we go again who was the greatest
warrior between arjuna and karna who was
the greatest warrior and so on and so
forth ad infinitum
arjun was the superior person the
superior human being and the superior
warrior i don't care what your favorite
tv serial shows you
i had recently spoken about this matter
in a couple of videos and i got
comments from some people saying i am
waiting for your apology video because
she had seen something else in her
favorite tv serial
so please
do not react
to data that doesn't agree with your
preconceived notions don't react
emotionally to it
react intelligently to it
karna was an inferior person he was not
a great human being
he was hot tempered he was impulsive
he was abusive
and
he was not the better warrior
tv series they need new controversies to
attract attention and eyeballs and trps
and that's why they will distort history
they will
back project present day
notions etc and and
world views and ideas into something
that happened many thousands of years
ago
so please
if you want to really understand the
mahabharata era
read a translation or read the actual
text read a translation in your native
language read a translation into hindi
read a translation into english read an
abridged version if necessary or read
the original sanskrit but you have to do
a reading complete reading once
otherwise who the hell do you think you
are to consider yourself an expert from
tv serials
are you kidding me
please please
approach the right
uh
please use the right approach when
examining historical events you don't
become an expert by watching a tv series
you become
well your mind is then filled with lies
if you see tv series please don't do
that
who conferred the title of the father of
the nation to mr gandhi and why well i
have
some people say it is mr tagore who did
that some people say it was somebody
else i recently saw a proclamation on
and a dictat by the british indian
government in 1938 i think which
which required all
government officials colonial government
officer officials to address mr gandhi
as not mr gandhi or mr mohandas gandhi
or mundus gandhi
this was an official
dictat
by the government of india the colonial
government of india so maybe they called
him mahatma and maybe somebody else
called him the father of the nation i
don't care who called him
father of the nation or mahatma it
doesn't matter
what matters is
we understand this individual this
person mr gandhi
factually
from the 21st century factual context
you need to form your opinion of this
gentleman
based on facts and data not based on
what other people have said about him in
the past
do not base your opinion on what others
have said in the past even if you may
respect that historian or love that
person please don't do that
that is a slippery slope then you will
never have your own
original thinking ever in your life
please talk about neeta's disappearance
not today
but soon
but soon i am not
the expert in this matter so maybe
i should bring in the relevant expert
don't you think
so it will happen soon
um all right what else do we have
i misunderstood your question from a
previous three stream tacitus is an
ancient roman historian
josephus is an ancient jewish historian
both of whom independently attest to
jesus christ
so today if i
independently attest to the flying
spaghetti monster does it bring the
flying spaghetti monster into
existence
do you understand the difference between
a claim and actual evidence
these two gentlemen you may be in awe of
them it's fine i i respect
your
right to believe them
that's fine
i do not consider that to be clinching
evidence but two guys 2000 or whatever a
thousand years ago made some claims
independently oh nice it's independent
claims
it doesn't matter do we have
archaeological evidence we have
archaeological evidence of julius caesar
we don't have archaeological evidence of
alexander
we don't have a shred of archaeological
evidence
of mr christ
and there are various other people for
whom we don't have enough archaeological
evidence
and for certain classes of people we
have to we have to agree that these are
mythological figures but certain other
figures
we have different criteria why is that
why do we have dual standards
there are ancient indian historians who
also have referred to various indian
historical figures but that is
unilaterally considered to be myths
so i'm applying the same standards my
dear friend and friends
there is no evidence whatsoever
that mr christ actually existed no hard
archaeological evidence
okay what else do we have um
let me take
a different question
as an aspiring theoretical physicist i
would like
if you gave a message to the next
generation of scientists
and the motivation to do something for
the greater good seek answers embrace
curiosity well what can i say to the
next generation of aspiring scientists
first of all
first of all study the fundamentals
study the fundamentals very thoroughly
spend the majority of your time learning
the fundamentals of your discipline
whether it is physics whether it is
chemistry it is biology
or some engineering discipline study the
fundamentals focus on that first if you
have the phenomenals right you can do
anything
and if you're a physicist theoretical
physicist please spend a lot of time
mastering the math math can get complex
but yeah it's no big deal you can learn
it secondly if you can master the
fundamentals always keep an open mind
don't close off your mind don't be
influenced by dogma there are so many
physicists and scientists
who have a dogmatic approach
we know what happened to subramaniam the
sheker he
did his research about black holes and
neutron stars as a graduate student
in the 1930s
and the eminent physicist
british physicist arthur eddington shot
it down he said there should be a law
against the star behaving in such a
manner
and because of this subramaniam tender
was marginalized for a couple of decades
at least even though other physicists
knew he was right
so this sort of group think has existed
forever in science in the 1950s and 60s
american doctors scientists used to
endorse smoking they used to appear in
tobacco ads i have shown this in the
past
google it
they were lying to the public
they were telling the public there is no
danger in tobacco smoke and smoking
right
and the same approach continues today in
a different context in the west
and they said don't go against the
science follow the science what i say is
the science what another scientist says
is lies
what sort of approach is this they're
politicizing science and they are
allowing themselves to be sold to the
highest
bidder so to the aspiring scientists i
would say please maintain your integrity
don't say things because you are paid to
say those things
half the news you hear today is lies and
behind all those lies are scientists
today i am not going into any specifics
but i think you all are intelligent
enough to understand what i'm saying
so that's what i would say
maintain your integrity
don't lie to yourself first of all
secondly focus on the basics the
fundamentals master your subject spend
hours hundred thousands of hours
doing that
and then
be curious embrace your curiosity
embrace your imagination and don't fall
for group think
so that's what i can say my friends
all right
please explain about umuah
those were my people
don't tell anybody
right
what do we have
okay
can you please explain more about hard
archaeological evidence
well
let's talk about the great
barbaric terrorist timur
do we have archaeological evidence for
him what is archaeological evidence
evidence you can excavate
so there is a mausoleum of this monster
in central asia
i don't remember which city it is in
look it up look it up
so his mausoleum is there it is present
inside the masolium there is a grave a
tomb
in which this guy's
bones reside in the early 20th century
the soviet uh a bunch of a number of
soviet scientists
opened the tomb
took out his bones
determined the date and all that they
determined it was it matched
the date at which uh during which timor
is known to have lived
they made a facial reconstruction and so
on
so that is hard tangible
archaeological evidence of the existence
of timur
similarly we have certain monsters who
are buried in india there is
archaeological evidence because it's
there
it's there
someday
right
now
what is the lack of archaeological
evidence
it means nothing exists
on the ground or under the ground that
would give
testimony to the fact that something
happened
for instance they claimed there was an
invasion of the aryans in india right
now if you look at the arkham
archaeological record in northern india
western india present-day pakistan
present-day gandha afghanistan
you will see not a single evidence of
any warfare no dead bodies thrown around
no bones with cut marks on them or fatal
wounds you don't see evidence of
destroyed or burned cities you see
nothing that is called lack of hard
archaeological evidence because there's
nothing that supports this claim
right so that is the difference between
the presence of archaeological evidence
and the absence of hard archaeological
evidence i hope that makes it
simple to understand
all right
uh
what else do we have
let me take another question
what role does art particularly visual
and fine arts play in a civilization why
has modern india produced
only a handful of these artists and how
was the situation in ancient times
because i believe it was great and how
can this be changed
art
is the barometer
of the progress of a civilization art is
an integral part of culture when we talk
about art we can there are multiple
layers to art multiple multiple
um
what do what should i call it
multiple of
artistic phenomena
literature is art poetry is art dance
dance forms or art music
is art painting sculpture all these are
forms of art right these are different
manifestations
these are different artistic
manifestations of a culture architecture
is art and you get the point
a a civilization
that is at its pinnacle is going to see
an outpouring and outburst of artistic
activity because a civilization that
that is at its peak is extremely
financially
prosperous
very high standards of living and
politically stable which means that
people have the time for leisure
activities such as
going and listening to a concert
a musical concert a drama play and they
have the time to invest in architecture
and painting and all that
so the more artistic a civilization is
the more the greater the artistic output
the higher
the level of advancement of the
civilization and the same goes for
science also science and technology
so art is a beautiful
and accurate barometer of the
level of advancement of a civilization
today
india is a broken civilization india is
no longer a civilization india is merely
a mediocre nation state with low
standards and very low per capita gdp
people even today their first
thought when it comes to the children is
that they should get a stable stable job
they should just survive
that is the first thing everybody has in
mind
and you if
if a kid wants to become an artist or a
sports person there is no money today in
that there is no state support
and therefore we have very little
artistic output in india today and
whatever is there is mediocre at best
there are very few
top quality artists there are some there
are some of them still around
but many of them are marginalized many
of them don't have any support
and art cannot flourish
without
patronage from wealthy people
either the artists themselves have to be
wealthy or they should have patronage
from the state or from society today
nothing of that sort exists the only art
today is bollywood which is garbage
it's garbage
and no disrespect to certain
bollywood certain people who are part of
bollywood i have
i do have respect i do respect certain
people in bollywood but those are few
and far between
right so that's the situation the
situation in ancient times was very
different we see outpouring of artistic
activity everywhere
all those
examples of art are today defaced broken
and vandalized by we know whom
how can it be changed first make india
strong and prosperous again
make india a civilization again
reject the colonial system which makes
india a nation state not a civilization
and then things will change
um
right what else do we have
rajkumar says how did humans learn the
most
scientific and advanced language
sanskrit
was it provided to us by some advanced
higher beings
it contains all the words that can
describe every aspect of life
languages evolve before sanskrit there
was the mother of sanskrit whatever it
was we don't know languages have been
evolving in the indian subcontinent for
70 000
or maybe slightly more than that years
right
so sanskrit did not appear out of out of
the heavens it evolved over time in
india over thousands of years
there is absolutely no evidence that it
was given to us by some advanced beings
if there is evidence i'll be happy to
accept it i have seen no such evidence
none none whatsoever
right
so sanskrit has evolved in the indian
subcontinent subcontinent over thousands
of years we don't quite know how long
ago
what we today recognized as sanskrit
first emerged it would have emerged out
of languages that were older than it and
those languages would be the roots of
sanskrit
and before those languages we had even
before even older languages we have lost
all the evidence
and all the data but
so that's how it evolved why is it so
advanced as a language because india was
a very advanced civilization
so language again is an example of how
advanced or backward
a culture or a civilization is
a language with thousands of synonyms
hundreds of synonyms for a certain word
is a very evolved language it means the
people were very peaceful very civilized
they had a lot of time to look at
nuances in the world
right
so that's how it is so it it gives you
an indication of what sort of culture
and society india was in the past which
it no longer is today
why is india's role in ww2 world war ii
always ignored but please don't ignore
it talk about it that's what i say i
haven't ignored india's own in the
second world war
there are certain
writers these days who are writing about
it certain people are talking about it
it will not be ignored if you don't keep
quiet
talk about it speak about it spread the
awareness learn about it do your own
research look at my older videos in
which i may have spoken about this
find other sources of information there
are books there is information online
educate yourself
and then talk about it don't stop
talking tell everybody
go tell everyone shout it from the
rooftops then it will be impossible to
ignore if everyone does this
uh
can you elaborate about these exotic
stars magnetars pulsars neutron stars i
have answered these questions in detail
look at my previous videos just search
it on my youtube channel
go to the search box
and type magnetar or pulsar or neutron
star within a fraction of a second you
will get the answer so i have answered
these questions in detail i'm glad your
answer asking these questions very
interesting uh
topics but i have already answered them
okay i can see lots of questions i've
answered before
uh i'm looking for some interesting
questions that i haven't taken off
before
okay
anime says
i am puzzled by your mention about india
being a hindu phobic country
yet i see everyone celebrating all our
festivals and cultural events with all
enthusiasm am i missing something my
dear friend you're missing a very big
deal of what's happening in india this
is why i say it's all there in front of
you but you can't see it
have you seen the indian constitution
have you seen it
and have you seen the articles 25 or 30
29 or 30
have you read them
no have you seen how india's
institutions operate
have you seen that the the
repeated bans on certain festivities
only when it comes to hinduism
have you seen how hinduism is portrayed
in your education system have you seen
or are you not able to see it
yes some people are celebrating the
festivals with certain enthusiasm
in almost every state you are seeing
bans
on various
manifestations of indian culture whether
it is in northern india western india
eastern india southern india i'm sure
it's not there in every state i am i
don't have all the data but you know
what
there are glaring examples in front of
everybody
but you are missing something
so what can i do for you sir
the entire system
all the institutions see how they
operate
you are educated all of you
please examine things meticulously and
thoroughly
it's all there in front of you
our constitution
is a foreign constitution
it doesn't
regard indian culture as anything worth
preserving or worth valuing it is not
even based or rooted in indian
civilizational values and you say that
india is not a hindu phobic country
what can i say sir what can i say
if you wish not to look at what the
situation is
feel free not to
okay
can you please comment on the city of
the monkey god found in the jungles of
honduras the monkey god carving is of no
other than a lord and um is it written
there in some script that it is lord
hanuman
there is a monkey god there okay let's
say i agree i've seen that
how do you know there's a connection
with blood
they also have monkeys everywhere there
we also have monkeys everywhere here
in india
is it not conceivable in your mind
that maybe they came up with the idea
independently i am not saying there is
no possibility that there may be a
connection i am not saying it but as of
today
we don't have any actual hard evidence
whether genetic evidence literary
evidence linguistic evidence cultural
evidence
that conclusively proves this
conclusively proves this there is
circumstantial evidence that indicates
that there may have been connections
but nobody has investigated that and
until anyone until somebody investigates
it scientifically we will not have any
evidence and therefore from the lack of
evidence today it is wrong
to draw connections and claim this is
not a new one who told you it is not on
the man
did you see it written somewhere
did you see a carving or an instruction
inscription that says it is hanuman
no
it's a monkey
they had lots of monkeys they still have
lots of monkeys maybe they also saw
see
the peoples the native peoples of
america north as well as south america
they were polytheistic people
in polytheism
you worship everything everything is a
manifestation of the divine
the sky the rivers the land
the trees the plants the animals the
people themselves there is divinity
everywhere
and therefore i am not surprised that
they saw
monkeys which are so intelligent and so
similar to us and they saw that as a
manifestation of divinity
that is present everywhere in a superior
manifestation perhaps of divinity and
that's why perhaps they
worshipped
their monkey god the same way
indians
worship lord numan
isn't it possible aren't there other
explanations that can also explain
the presence of a monkey god then how
can you only focus on one explanation
and and and
blank out everything else
as of today there are multiple
explanations that all are equally
plausible
and there is no evidence or data that
eliminates certain explanations and
therefore we cannot make the claim that
this monkey card is a lot of neumann we
simply can't make it it would be
completely incorrect
at this juncture in the absence of
evidence of data to make this claim
but i'm not saying it's impossible
i would what i would want is indian
archaeologists
indian scientists
communicate and connect with their
colleagues in south america maybe
visit there for a year or two and do do
their own independent research with the
help of the local experts then we will
have a better idea but our experts
they are
unfortunately not doing anything
so given this status that we have we
cannot make this claim
all right
is it true that because of the british
rule all the diverse cultures of india
felt the need to be united and this
initiated a feeling of nationalism
india has one culture
india has one culture with lots of local
manifestations it is not diverse
cultures it's only one culture which has
lots of local manifestations
okay let me let me give you some
evidence for for for a change
give me a second let me find something
an image that i can show you
what do we have
let me share an image with all of you
just give me a give me a second
i'm doing it
okay take a look at this please
please take a look at this what does
this show you
what does this map show you
okay let's take a bigger look at this
so this is
a plot
of the various shakti peats across the
indian subcontinent
and the shankaracharya matas
right
the red
line
indicates
some of the shakti peats in india
now this is evidence of different
cultures is it
are these different religions different
cultures
or is it the same religion the same
culture
and do you see it is it extends from
balochistan to assam from from
from punjab or or rather gandhar all the
way to southern india
so how can you say we had different
cultures across india
don't you see india was always united
from this the same culture unified by
the same culture same belief system same
philosophy same spirituality same
civilization
so on what basis can we make the claim
that we had diverse culture and the
british unified us because they
instilled in a feeling of nationalism
if there was no nationalism before the
british came how did the shankaracharya
find
open arms waiting for him wherever he
want whenever he went in india
if he was to be regarded as somebody
from a different culture would he be
accepted
please my dear friends think logically
all the information like i say is there
in front of you
but somehow you are not able to see
it you have to find a way to open your
eyes
all the information is there in front of
you please use your own intelligence you
are all
intelligent people
you may have been led to believe by your
teachers that you are not intelligent
your teachers are lying
you are all intelligent
all of you please please discover the
intelligence within and use it
um
anish says your thoughts on the recent
laps in the pm's security unacceptable
unacceptable it shows
how soft of a state india is and it
shows how
disunited and fragmented india is it
shows how many enemies india has on its
own soil we don't need enemies outside
we have more enemies inside than outside
so what happened shows that what else
can i say unacceptable
i hope there are consequences
i wish there are consequences for this
sort of
incident
here we go again
it is not true that india has been a
single polity before the british
okay i need to this is unacceptable like
i don't need to see this sort of thing
if you don't agree then please don't
don't watch listen to me speak
the thing is i show data and evidence
and you have you rely some people rely
on what their beliefs are even if you
show all the data in front of them they
will say no
my name
go please
ah
right
make a debate with science journey
channel no
no thank you
i don't do debates and i don't do
reactions i do my own thing
i hope
i am doing what adds real value to you i
have no interest in shouting matches and
debates and all that nonsense that you
see everywhere on your um
so called news channels no no no none of
that over here
all right um
what else do we have
okay this is an older question what
why during star formation during due to
enormous pressure
fusion starts instead of forming a solid
round planet like object
what is the state of matter at the
moment
just before the fusion starts at the
core of these clouds
and what does the core of gaseous
planets like jupiter
why is it liquid and not solid
well you know what you can take
hydrogen gas turn it into a liquid by
compressing it and making it cold enough
and you can even
freeze it solid
at around around 20 degrees
above absolute zero so it's possible
now inside a planet like jupiter which
is a gas giant it has a very small rocky
core that's what we believe
and its interior is highly compressed
because of the enormous
mass of the planet
so all of this mass is pressing down on
the interior of the planet and it it
makes
uh the hydrogen inside jupiter
very very dense
at some stage it becomes what you would
call a liquid it's actually a fluid
and inside it is believed that there is
a state a stage a
region where you have what's called
metallic hydrogen where hydrogen
actually acts as a conductor of
electricity
right
so that's what it is jupiter the
interior is very hot it's not cold
it's very hot because of the immense
pressure and same goes for saturn
now when it comes to star formation the
stars are much more massive than jupiter
the minimum
mass you would need to ignite fusion is
about 93 95 jupiter masses
so that's the minimum mass of hydrogen
fuel you need to ignite fusion how does
fusion ignite because of the compression
because of gravity
so the upper layers
pulled push down on the interior layers
because they're heavy
and
eventually when there is sufficient mass
it is
at the core of the star
there is so much pressure
such incredible forces at work
that atoms of hydrogen start fusing
together because of this pressure and
that is the fusion reaction which gives
rise to helium and that is the ignition
point of
of nuclear fusion in a newborn star so
when you look at the sun
if you do
that is a fusion reaction in process it
is a nuclear fusion reaction a nuclear
fusion explosion
that you are seeing
so the state of matter we don't quite
know exactly what it will be there are
certain hypothesis but what i can say is
that it is incredibly dense and
compressed hydrogen
at the core of a star at the moment that
nuclear fusion
is triggered off
okay let's take a couple more questions
um
what's wrong with steady state cosmology
it doesn't fit the data that we have
observational evidence observational
data steady state cosmology says the
universe has always existed it's been
here forever it's immortal nothing
changes the state stays the same as what
we kind of observed today but the data
and the evidence that we have from
observational astronomy completely
is completely in contradiction with this
with this belief
what we find is that the universe is
expanding
and the expansion is accelerating the
further you are the further the galaxies
are blue shifted
and so on so we have evidence that
completely contradicts this this
this theory
right so that's what's wrong with it it
doesn't
fit observed data
you can come up with theories but then
your theories have to be able to match
observed data and they have to be able
to predict
phenomena that we that we witness
so steady state cosmology doesn't
doesn't uh
fulfill
these conditions and that's why it is no
longer
a theory that's accepted
all right
[Music]
okay coach deb says
the education system is utter crap
um so what should a team do
can hindu make india's superpower role
of viruses in india okay let me take the
first question i will
otherwise it will take
a long time if the education system is
terrible what should a team do educate
yourself regardless the education system
is something you have to endure it is
something you have to tolerate
because as of today you still need a
degree to get a good job
so just put up with it get your degree
whatever it is
your whatever degree it is in whatever
field you're interested in but apart
from that concentrate on acquiring
genuine knowledge
today
you can acquire knowledge from your
phone
anytime on demand
all the information
in the world
is available at your fingertips
use that
try to understand who you are what your
true aptitudes are what your real
strengths are
you should also know your weaknesses but
focus on the strengths
and strengthen them further acquire
skills that are in
in tune
with your aptitudes and your strengths
you can acquire skills for free today
you can acquire you can go through and
learn entire courses online on whatever
field you're interested in
and
what you should do is spend the first 10
years minimum of your adult life
investing in yourself in your personal
development
acquire skills acquire experience
acquire
knowledge acquire wealth please acquire
wealth
learn what wealth is how to acquire it
and once you are sufficiently mature
enough then
you can do something for the country
with the knowledge the skills the
experience and the wealth that you have
acquired
so that's what you can do
the education system is is an
unavoidable evil today so just put up
with it i think in the next 10 years
it's going to be completely obsolete
but as of today kids have to do it
unfortunately when they should actually
be spending that time investing their
time learning real world skills that can
solve the problems of the 21st century
the education system does nothing of
that it turns children
brilliant
intelligent
bright children into sheep it is not the
fault of the kids
that they don't know how to see the big
picture that they don't know how to look
for information
it's something that is hammered out of
them you know
so please recognize the fact that the
education system is
seeks to turn you into sheep it seeks to
convert you into a clerk or a peon from
the colonial days
don't allow this to happen don't allow
your teachers to destroy your creativity
and your curiosity
invest in yourselves
and
you can change the country when you
reach a certain age
so i wish you all the best
the very best
does yeti or bigfoot exist today we have
no evidence i'd be happy if they existed
but we have no evidence
no
incontrovertible evidence
all right where else are we
what do you think of the about the right
to veto used by the permanent members of
the security council
and how this right has probably not been
used to solve any major issue the
intention of this veto
power is not to solve any issues
there are five permanent members of the
security council and this situation
reflects the ground reality that was
in existence in 1945
so the five
winning powers
the five most powerful powers
became the five security council
permanent members india was offered this
as we have discussed this before
multiple times in the great mr nehru
rejected that and he said give it to
china so china became the permanent
member and and
the objective
of the system is to consolidate their
hold on power it is not to solve any
issue
right
so the
the u.n has been frozen
in in in place as if it is as if we are
still in 1945
it reflects the power structure of 1945
it doesn't reflect the ground realities
of today
the uk is a american vasal today
it is not a great power anymore
they have pretensions of grandeur but
they are all misplaced
they are
essentially
worthless pointless today the uk
they can no longer be regarded as a
great power the french again are not
that great a power the french i would
say are much superior to the british
when it comes to the geopolitical power
so the british don't deserve to be there
whatsoever
and the other nations the uk
the uk the us the ussr which is russia
today
china
and who else is there france yeah so we
need to reconfigure the un to make it
more reflective of the ground realities
today and it is not designed to solve
any major issues the ui is not designed
to solve issues it is designed as an
instrument for projecting power
the chinese are doing it brilliantly
with the who which is which is an arm of
the u.n and the americans that have done
it time and again
when it suits them they will say follow
the us the u.n
resolutions when it doesn't suit them
they will completely ignore and go
against against u.n resolutions so
that's how it is
india had the opportunity but our
so-called leader
rejected rebuffed these opportunities
multiple times so what needs to happen
is
india needs to go its own way forget
about the unsc become a major power in
your own right understand what power is
and develop that
all right my dear friends
let me take one more question one more
question for today
all right
um
i have answered all these questions
all of these questions before
um
ask me interesting questions guys
do we have something
okay let me take this one why did some
indian scholars ancient indian scholars
go to the island of sokotra and where
ancient indians ever interested in
conquering madagascar
this is the first time i'm hearing the
claim that indians went to sokotra what
evidence do we have sir
do we have evidence please mention what
evidence you have i have never come
across any evidence that indian scholars
in ancient times went to so-called of
course my knowledge is not influen
universal i may not know something
in that case
if you have
some source that you know
of you could share it here
or maybe i will do some independent
research on my own and see if there is
any evidence
that
indian scholars went to socotra
so
so that's what i can say
do we have anything else
india had just three unicorns in 2016
after startup india scheme india has 84
universe unicorns in 2021.
we were only behind the us china in
terms of unicorn in 2021
future of our startup ecosystem i think
it's brilliant
i have criticized the government many
times in the past
this is something the government needs
to be uploaded for
upload it not uploaded
yeah
so this is great
84 unicorns out of
from a number of just just three five
years before that so that's a big
explosion in the number of unicorns that
is great i would like to see this trend
continue
why why can't india have the
most number of unicorns
uh in the world
so i think the government is doing
something right
it needs to continue that and
if if it continues that when india's
future is bright india's startup
ecosystem
will do well in that case
all right
okay that brings me to the end of
today's
session thank you very much for your
questions
tomorrow we have a special episode
the first episode of the
of the
abhijit chapter podcast and tomorrow's
guest is the
acclaimed historian and writer anuj dar
same channel 9 pm india time tomorrow i
look forward to seeing you all there
it's going to be a very interesting
discussion until then take care and i
will see you soon bye